alright welcome to idea cafe for
February 25th today's question is what
steps can we take towards collective
curation or distributed leadership or
whatever you want to call the thing that
doesn't really have a word that is it is
how do we get shit done without a
central leadership body how do we do it
we've been talking about last couple
weeks so who would like to start
I can always start it's a very it's a
very very tricky notion I don't have a
huge amount to say here other than the
points out that it's a very very tricky
notion because we are fundamentally not
used to working that way right we are
used to having a person in charge it was
responsible for whatever the thing is
and you know that some people doing
different people doing different ways
but essentially that you know they're
they they are the ones who direct things
and so when something goes wrong people
turn to them for direction as to how to
go about putting it right you know what
I mean there and we are this is ground
into us from a very very very young age
I mean if you think of your 13 years of
schooling right and the above and be all
it above and beyond all else it taught
you to shut up do as you're told and pay
attention to authority figures right and
so that this you know in game B language
it's that it's that broadcast modality
right we've been trained to be receptive
to broadcast and not to take
responsibility for our own little bit of
the thing that we can take
responsibility for so that's that's all
I have to say I think it's going to be
very very very tricky just because we're
not used to it that's that's all I have
to say
all right French are Kira wanna go I'll
go
Eric I appreciate what you shared and I
was reminded of a conversation that I
heard the that Jordan Hall had and where
he was talking about sort of the history
of God what got us here and prior to you
know groups getting beyond the size of
Dunbar number it was more of a
collective decision you know there there
was more of a collective or it was
possible to have more of a collective
decision-making and then once things get
got beyond the Dunbar number then we had
to have people in positions of authority
and it was no longer about collective
decision-making and so the thing that I
think in terms of steps to make towards
being able to do that is a couple of
things one is the ability to take
responsibility but that and and this is
something that's been coming up in
various conversations which is
recognizing that like something might
not be your fault and take and taking
responsibility like there there's this
thing of if if it's if if you're
responsible for it and it doesn't and
something doesn't go right it's your
fault
and moving away from a fault-finding
paradigm towards a towards something
else and I and and I'll be open to what
word might make more sense but it's
moving away from fault and towards a
toward responsibility but also towards
okay what is what can we learn from this
not who's not whose fault is it
and I'm reminded of something that
happens in the tech world of a like a
like going over when something goes
wrong going over it not
the intention of finding out whose fault
it is but finding out how the system can
improve and I think that's an important
part and there's individually what we
can do to take responsibility and be
comfortable with that and that is
something that you know I think there
are certain forms of responsibility that
we're comfortable that that people are
comfortable with and then other ones
where it's like no I can't I I can't
possibly handle that I can't I can't
take responsibility for that and
understanding or and getting comfortable
and I think like all things game be
getting comfortable with being
uncomfortable because the more I can be
and being comfortable with the ambiguous
with there isn't somebody there isn't
some authority figure that I can go to
who's going to give me the answer there
isn't necessarily going to be certainty
in how to move forward and getting
comfortable with that and and because as
long as there's a person in authority
who can give me an answer then I'm
certain than I am then I have certainty
and I know you know there's an expert
there who can who can tell me and but if
I don't have that I'm like wow what do I
do
and and so getting comfortable with
ambiguity I think is a huge part in
moving us towards the collective you
know and like I think of you know
curation leadership sense making like
all of those different things curation
is an interesting word and so when when
we open it up for a larger discussion
I'd be like I'll be interested in
hearing kind of what what other people's
takes are on that on on the word
curation in particular so that's what I
got
kyaa you want to go Brent you want me to
go it's going to us doesn't matter all
right
Oh
um because I think I usually go last
whoever else go first the last week I
don't Brett would last this is a topic
that just like last week where we set
the topic and then shit happened this is
kind of what I wanted to talk about and
then one of my communities that I've
been following for a really long time
fell
didn't fall apart but it feels to me
like it fell apart because the person it
centered around had this fall from grace
he's kind of entered the me2 movement
with his own story and all these people
that that are his clients that he's
tried to sleep with and slept with and
had relationships with and whether he's
in a main relationship or not it's very
confusing he hasn't yet had a statement
but the fragility of leadership that
when you have a central authority and
any cracks form they fall and then the
surrounding community falls and the
fragility that comes with that doesn't
really happen in the case of like what I
talked about last week with my community
where this person may have a conflict
but the community is not going to stop
because we have a conflict at the same
time there's no one to go to really
there's the processing team but they're
trying to do it faster than they did
last time and I still have yet to get an
email a week and a bit later and so it's
like the how do we as a taught as
sovereign individuals take ownership of
our own lives our own feelings when we
want someone in leadership over us or
when we want to be a leadership over
somebody else and at the same time how
does shit get done how does conflict get
resolved how does approach a project
move forward either by having a central
you know embodied group of people that
can have a conversation to come to
consensus or or not and it's something
that we have to play in and with because
we're never gonna get to game B if we
can't figure out how to have distributed
leadership how did not leave it up to
someone else how to take on what is ours
and leave for other people what is
theirs and organize it in a way where
it's not completely chaotic you know
like who to go to with an issue or what
type of people to go to with an issue
and there's multiple people
you can go to and so I think there are
solutions in this realm but we're so
used to it being this top-down hierarchy
that we all want that like we are all
like well wait who's the leader who do I
go to who do I complain about and then
when the leader falls apart
there really isn't to anyone the thing
falls apart of that and that we need to
have resilience beyond a single or a
tiny group of leadership we need to be
able to have those interconnected
relationships and own our own
sovereignty and that is what I'm sure
I'm done
I'm always fine you know what the topic
is like two minutes before I jump on the
call which is fun because it's like I
mean I I like it because it's I'm not
prepared right then it's like it is a
good topic what how can we collectively
curate because curation is implicit in
many platforms and communities like New
York Times big thing and most critics
are kinda critical because of that like
what they choose to put in and what they
choose to leave out right so there's a
there's a lot of decision-making there
whether it's by individuals or committee
and there's a lot of curation in this
space too and like rebel wisdoms space
and I don't want to crap on them too
much but but you know along the lines of
the things I've said for for a couple
years is some of their stuff is good
some of its bad right and what they are
doing fundamentally is curating right
curating these different thinkers Oh
Daniel dr. Berger Jordan Hall and and
it's you know it creates a conversation
around those attractors mm-hmm but you
know it's also what what they're
platforming like all the intellectual
dark web stuff and and what they're
ignoring or what they're blocking which
is in any type of criticism of that type
of stuff so hmm like just it's in the
general sense to come back to this
question of curation it's it's a complex
question of what we eat value as as a
group as individuals and you know come
coming back to the issues you guys are
raising about what's difficult to
contend with um you know I think we we
select things we curate things on our
own feeds that that are comfortable
right even if they're on the face of it
very interesting and very provocative it
might still appeal to something within
us that is an appeal to simplicity like
oh I prefer the curation of things this
mmm that's only like two and a half
minutes but mmm I really can't think of
anything else you're allowed to end
early it's not a try to draw it out five
minutes so now we can all that Mike if
we want to and have an open conversation
as we do what came up for me this week
in both my thing in my individual
community and this thing that is
happening with Kyle sees is that in me
in my own personal being I'm kind of
having fun with the drama and I don't
like that about me like I'm like I'm
like like when the community member
email me back and I'm like I told you to
email me and I write it out was and it
was a piece that likes the drama that
wants the drama to continue and like
he'd seek you know going to this
person's Facebook page because Kyle sees
hasn't posted anything so it's only this
one person who's a Facebook page that is
has has all this stuff on it because his
is way to curate it has to go through
admin so it's never coming out if it's
on his page but it's on his other page
and like wanting to know what's up
wanting to know the next piece of gossip
and the next piece of stuff and owning
that in myself and sitting with the
uncomfortableness of that like and yet
I'd have very little drama in my life so
it is like what am I here to learn but
like that piece I'm good with so what
piece might here to learn what's
uncomfortable let sit with it but it's
also the need to like almost like keep
the drama going like oh what's next once
what can I poke what can i and it's like
owning that that piece and me so that
I'm not doing that in the world and not
perpetuating that can I can I just
because this is a line that I think for
me anyway needs needs to be sort of
clearly delineated as that between
distributes the notion of distributed
leadership and distributed curation
because leadership you know there's
nothing in one person's hands and it can
be fluid and it can move around but the
idea of leadership being distributed I
mean either do it
there was a Oh God was it during occupy
economy anyway there's this whole thing
oh no we don't have any leaders right
and you know it without a go-to person
in a leadership sense without a go-to
person there is no who's actually
responsible for making sure this thing
happens you know what I mean and so you
know doesn't mean you have to have one
person in charge all the time or that
they have to be also practical
dictatorial it doesn't mean any of that
but but I don't think you can have
distributed leadership I almost think
it's a contradiction in terms the
curation thing I think that that can't
be done by one by one person or by a
small group people write something if
and so this is coming back to what Kira
asked in her opening thing about what we
mean by the actual word curation and for
me it's a it's a it's a tending it's a
looking after it's a maintaining it's a
caring about right it's it's got those
sorts of those sorts of aspects to it
and so that has to be a collective
effort because if you're curating a
thing whatever that thing might be
trying to make sure that it doesn't
spoil doesn't go off doesn't get ruined
in whatever way then everybody needs to
have their eyes open and most
importantly everybody needs to have some
kind of con vision some kind of
understanding of what the thing is that
they are trying to curate what is the
actual essence where is the nature of
the thing that they are trying to curate
what are they trying to keep it as Eric
what came up for me as you were talking
about that and you know I've mentioned
before that one of the communities that
I'm part of this is 12-step communities
and in 12 there's the 12 steps but
unless you're part of the community
there's something else which is called
the 12 traditions and that is how to how
the group have how the group works
together so the 12 steps is for your
individual development but the the 12
traditions is about the group and
there's one in particular that is our
leaders are chosen to gov to serve not
to govern and so most of you know
every AAA group is is completely
independent there's no you know there
are there is a central office there is
you know there there is some central
leadership but ultimately all of the
power rests in the hands of each
individual group and then each
individual group has service positions
and the people who are elected to the
the service positions they have a set
amount of time and like in the case of
the person who's the secretary who you
could essentially call the leader of the
group they have a set format of what
they're supposed to run but one of the
things that they do is they ask people
to come in and chair the meeting and the
chairing the meeting means they come in
and share their story and so for a
six-month period of time they are
serving the group they are coming the
end and part of what it what they are
doing is curating who is going to come
in and talk to the group and there's
something about that that I like that
you know there's a recognition that the
group can't be completely an hour it
can't be complete anarchy there needs to
be somebody who is coming in and unlocks
the door and turns on the lights and you
know makes sure that and then there's
somebody who's making sure that the rent
gets paid me to end that the the coffee
gets made and the chairs get put out and
but it's that distinct name of they're
elected to serve not to govern but to
serve like that's such a such a
fundamental part of a a that it's like
when I look out in the world and I'm
like why can't we elect people to serve
not you know I mean it's all supposed to
and so yeah that's just Eric as you were
sharing that was what came to mind is
like a a as a great example of of that
I'm not very interesting because when
Eric was talking I camp for me was this
idea of curation is about
the project and leadership is about like
organizing the people and keeping like
the conflict in alignment that was just
like the distinction between the two and
like in in a and and 12-step programs
there's the mission which is stay sober
but like you can never even even stink
tably no I can't be responsible for your
sobriety we can get all the interplay
and all this but like the the project is
our collective sobriety that you're here
how many days how many hours hope that
you're sober and then the bigger piece
of like but there is no I can't be in
control of you and you can't be in
control of me it's it's your ownership
for you because what also came up was
this idea that like there is no leader
to go to but no group most groups don't
have leaders to go to right when we talk
about any identity politics where it's
like well women or men or queers or
straight people or sis or trans it's
like they don't have meetings right they
don't get together and come up with a
tenant's and like this is what we're
gonna say is is is our is our goal and
is our like the only thing they have in
common is our identity yet we do
constantly group them together and kind
of say like like why do women like
having their their chair pulled out and
not like having their chair pulled out
because we're different and in different
moments and different circumstances like
there's something about its kind of okay
we don't have leadership because we're
not supposed to at the same time then
owning who do you go to to turn the
lights on to get the coffee done like
having a non Anarchy organization that
also owns you're responsible for
yourself that we have a mission that
needs curation what came up for me
Jubilee as you were sharing was you know
one of the interesting things about
12-step is the thing that binds the
group together is survival like you
don't end up in a unless you have no you
know it's like unless you're you're kind
of out of options and you stay because
that is the group of people that helped
you like get your life back on track
and keep yourself alive and
there's a and there's there's a magic in
there there's a certain amount of magic
that happens in that space that you know
because yeah if if you have a group of
women like what you know like a a has a
has a purpose it hasn't you know you
know one of the traditions our primary
purpose is to stay sober and help other
alcoholics that's you know that's what
our purpose is and so but like in these
other groups like not having that clear
purpose and in not having a clear
purpose and being difficult to have any
sense of direction nothing to curate
right there's no purpose and there's
nothing to curate that's right yeah
that's the whole thing exactly right
that shared sense of this is what we're
trying to do and you know preserving
that whatever that thing is I mean in
that case in your instance it's well
yeah what would at that that's that's
that's what curation centers around
right is recognizing what the thing is
and seeking to preserve it and maintain
it which i think is where we can go to
for the foundation is like survival and
creating his trading game be is also
about survival the issue is we don't
have sobriety as the thing right like
we're not like we all have a different
idea what the first step is towards game
being let alone what game he is even if
actually we might agree with what game
he is and it's somewhat utopian society
we don't agree with how to get there we
don't agree with the first step and we
don't even really agree with what that
looks like because of all the things
that we can't see in our own our own
vision but if we were to approach it
from like a 12 step program that game a
is what we're all addicted to even if
we'd want it gone I ain't like we know
it has this horrible impact on our lives
in the lives of others can we show up
have the conversations in order to move
it forward and that's it right just have
the conversations curate that curate
that how you find a group
and what are the bare minimum of rules
to be part of that group so that the
group itself can come up with more more
rules right like if I'm in any town and
I need an a a meeting I can find out
where the closest one is that doesn't
happen without a central authority right
but it does but what I mean is it
doesn't like you need to have some kind
of curation of that right otherwise
where do I go to find out yeah because
like there's an app that was built by
somebody you know just by by someone who
like you know collected all the
information from the various you know
because each disk knew there's districts
and each district has a central office
and and so there is some manner of
organization but it's very very loose if
someone's still going to put it on the
database or and take them off when the
groups disband and when you go and put
them on you know I mean there there is
still a level of curation involved by
someone write some somehow someone has
to do all that shit well and it's it you
know I mean it's interesting that you
know again I bring the things that I
have learned to the game be things to
the game be space and it's like there
are certain fundamental things that you
learn that that you learn and it
twelve-step and like it's like things
like one day at a time what's the next
indicated you know in a a they say
what's the next right action but I could
never deal with that because I could
never hit figure out what was the right
thing to do so I said what's the next
indicated action and you know dealing
with okay what's happening today and how
do you do that collectively as a group
it's like there's a lot of trying to
figure out okay how do we get to the top
of the mountain but we don't even know
how to take a first step and like that
when I came when I came in I had I had a
mentor who just he kept telling me stop
looking at the top of the mountain look
down at your feet
where are your feet he's like over and
over again cuz I kept going I don't know
how to figure anything out like I was
just completely crazy and I had no idea
how to figure out how to get from where
I was to where I thought I was supposed
to be or and it was like okay just focus
on where you are and but I don't know
how but it's like how do we
you that collectively a proposal I
suggest that we call what cure is
talking about curation Oh which aspect
curation like there is it sure not the
truth you let's aim it after but like
that focusing where you are instead of
where you need to get to it helps to
kind of know around where you want to
get to but then if you're so focused on
the destination then you can't take the
first step and you also don't realize
all the ways you have to go like this to
get there right it's like oh this is off
the path and this is and in truly owning
that we all just need to see where our
feet are right where are you
it also for me anyway it helps me have a
lot more compassion for where anybody is
because it's not about them getting to
the destination I may feel I want them
to get to it's about where they actually
are and seeing them helping them GPS
that right like let's figure out where
you are and then where do you want to
get to if that's even a thing we need to
know yeah right well your thoughts on
collective curation mmm curation is
without knowledge
yeah a lot along the lines of the bad
joke I just made I think the difference
is between like just you know cataloging
a bunch of related stuff under a certain
theme which is a kind of typical notion
of curation like with art mm-hmm and
organizing information or content in a
similar way but to have more of a
transform a transformative effect right
so mm-hmm it's just trying to index ting
isn't that just indexing what you're
talking about indexing would be just
more like
choosing an index according the
information better wouldn't actually
affect the kind of guidelines for what's
collected I guess but like I'm not I'm
not doing the point justice but you know
along the lines of what what what
they're saying to about game a is like
we're trying to get over the game an
addiction it can have parallels with AAA
like that I think that's interesting
because you're not just you're not just
curating you know information about
alcohol or whatever systems change in
this case like there's an actual goal
and it's a process we have to go through
together and commit commit to together
because like if we take it as seriously
as as a getting rid of this game a a
kind of pathology or cancer or addiction
of course it's much more complex so we
have to curate and weed out kind of what
what the what the patterns are within us
that that has become so normalized and
that's what happens with with drugs and
alcohol to is you just kind of lose
sight of the context and in which all
this stuff is happening you know so I
think there's something to be said for
this kind of a curation where where we
kind of look you know look to the goal
and look beyond our present problems
with with getting there and like kind of
again in the sense of a like to
subordinate yourself to to the process
and whatever whatever feelings you might
have liked it like it must be very
difficult right so you have to work
through the internal stuff and also just
the kind of external physical reality
based stuff that creates that addiction
I also really like that frame of game a
as an addiction right and treat it as
you would do addiction to alcohol or
drugs or sex or whatever in a 12-step
program I really like that frame the
problem with it is the alcohol addiction
for example is really it's a simple
thing right you're addicted to alcohol
you know you're addicted to alcohol you
know it's it's it's it's a simple thing
whereas game a is not a simple thing in
the same way as Brent said you've got a
in order for it to work in a 12-step
kind of way in order to have it to Kleck
the clarity and the power that the
simplicity of you know stay sober right
stay at Sobers say alive keep your life
together you know that the simplicity
and power of that is lost in the
complexity of game a there's no one
thing that you can point to to say
that's what I have to stop doing or
that's what I need to start doing right
there's it's much much much more busy
and complex than that well on the one
hand I agree with you that you you know
it's it's not as simple as you know
having a 30 day without you know 30 days
without buying something you know how
many years have I been sober from Game a
it is not it I don't think it is nearly
as simple for someone who's an alcoholic
of I'm an alcoholic
like it takes years for them to for
people to work through all of the so
easy I said simple they're very very
different things right yeah but but the
the aspect of coming to the realization
of what is what what is it that I am
actually but you know what what is it
that is causing the the problem and in a
lot of cases
it's there you know alcohol is what a
symptom of the problem and part of part
of a a is taking an inventory and and
starting to recognize oh I'm addicted to
the drama I'm addicted to absolutely get
what you're saying so what would be the
equivalent of alcohol in this analogy
for game a what would be the thing that
we do in game a which isn't the problem
itself but is the symptom of the problem
one of the things I would say is an
addiction to certainty okay is I need to
know that you know I need to have this
sense of certainty and at least that's
that that was the first that was the
first word that popped into my head when
you yeah what about the rest of you what
would be you know if we're going to use
that frame and so the problem isn't
actually in addiction to alcohol that's
a symptom of the problem but what is
what is the equivalent of the drinking
too much alcohol what's the what's for
you the one symptom of game a that is
obviously game a from unit comes with
certainty it's judgements judgments of
others and judgments of myself if I was
to just kind of copy the the pattern
here I would say rationality right
because cuz we're talking about kind of
abstractions and like the idea of you
know critical theory is largely the
heads you know reason and rationality
taken to it's absurd conclusion is is
totalitarianism so we we see a lot of
that
it's called instrumental reason right
apply throughout the 20th century that
it's you know scientific thinking but
like doesn't have moral ends necessarily
it's just instrumental
but but aside from that abstraction like
of course concretely people talk about
addiction to oil and that's not just a
kind of individual addiction like it is
a dependency that we've created but it's
also like it's not apt enough to think
of it as a personal addiction because
it's so instrumental and in fact rather
than internalizing the costs like with
Al
or smoking which are also externalize
but with oil it's mostly externalize you
know it's negative externalities so uh
yeah we're addicted to fossil fuels
right and this is a macro you know
cultural addiction that we've been
wrestling with for decades and how do we
you know all the questions come up like
okay we we know this is the case now
what do we do how do we commit to an
alternative etc right and it's it's
taking a lot longer than it should
I'd like to bring it right I appreciated
what you said there and this what came
up for me is sort of another frame that
comes from again the a a world which is
recognizing that something that was at
one point a tool now be now no longer
being a tool so for most people who are
alcoholics alcohol at one point served
like a purpose of it it made them looser
it made it you know it helps them deal
with anxiety it's a self medicate you
know it's a self medicating and how and
then at a certain point it becomes a you
know something that was a tool becomes a
detriment and and that and its Brent
that's what I thought of when you know I
thought of that but I up but what I also
thought of was okay if we thought of the
dependency on fossil fuel as a symptom
what are the things underneath that like
I thought of okay what are the things
that fossil fuel facilitates it fossil
it facilitates travel and you know and
like does the does are does releasing
our our dependence on fossil fuel like
mean we don't from stop traveling like
or you know how yeah
so what what are the sort of what are
the things that fossil fuel facilitates
and that because that's ultimately like
with with the inventory and AAA it's
like okay what are the things that I was
afraid to do that alcohol gave me the
courage to do yeah and I think that is
like also framing it as an addiction
like the 12-step program is mainly for I
believe abstinence type addictions right
like that's why it's 30 days sober I
don't know if they use the 12-step
program in like food addiction because
you I do they I feel like I want to it
is it is used there are some other
models that are more because there's
what's called a process addiction like
anorexia would be considered a process
addiction SLA which is sex love
addiction is a process addiction you're
not necessarily going to go forever
without sex but it's changing your but
but it's it's changing your relationship
to it and then al-anon which is the the
sister program to AAA which is the like
if you're in relationship to an
alcoholic you tend it tends to distort
your own thinking and al-anon like you
they talk about al-anon slips all the
time so it's not clear it's just how
long have you been in the program how
long have you been working at it so it's
it a a originally yes it's this this
concrete thing but it's like being in
the process of recovery and I think that
game B is a process of recovering some
things that we used to have that we like
Eric what you talked about and initially
of you know being conditioned to look
for a leader I don't know that that's
always been you know that that's always
been the case and that and recovering
that ability for collective intelligence
that I think might have it that I think
might have existed in the past so I
don't that answers your question Jubilee
yeah no and I think it is
like I didn't realize there was a
distinction a process addiction it's
what we need right because it's we can't
just like take away we can't just take
away our need for certainty or
leadership or I don't know that's not
but to own it in ourselves well at the
same time allowing that we are not
responsible for anybody else's sobriety
which even I know I've been very
responsible for like I'm like I'm here
to save the entire world looking if
they're like I am responsible for all of
it and it's like both owning that and
not owning it at the same time that it's
not all on me it's not mine and at the
same time how I do that is by
concentrating on mine a constraint on my
addictions and what I can do about the
feelings and sensations in my body and
my actions while hopefully helping other
people do that as well because it is
like a group thing that we're going
through yeah we somewhat strayed from
the initial point of the conversation
which was how does one go about laying
the stats for collective curation I've
got a related point I just it just
popped in my head earlier and I thought
it's relevant there's there's a Facebook
group I forget the exact name it's like
manda modern art and philosophy possibly
and it's it's a it's curated mm-hmm in
in in the best sense of the word by a
guy named David O'Donoghue and he's a
philosopher from Iowa and a bunch of us
actually met him in Kiev it was a a good
interesting cross-fertilization and so
he curates a lot of meta modern art
great and it's something I've wanted to
see for a long time but it's a difficult
thing to curate like what what is it
what is Matt a modern art and you know
in some sense it's whatever whatever the
curator says it says it is you know but
but there's been a lot of lot of super
just gorgeous
interesting thought-provoking art posted
there
and on a regular basis too so that that
takes a lot of time and effort you know
and I curate various things but nothing
to that degree and with that kind of
consistency so I appreciate that but
it's also interesting because because I
clash with David over politics because
he's in Iowa and he wanted to UM caucus
for Pete Budaj edge and and I've been
saying for months like butta judge is
not gonna pan out he's not he's a very
neo liberal candidates very very
centrist very moderate it's what we've
seen before it's not what people want
and it's easy to get wrapped up in
Pete's rhetoric and Obama energy but but
you know Pete's curating a certain
political message and I don't a lot of
people don't agree with it and so it
just goes to the point of curation like
we can we can curate different things
but then people have will have different
opinions in different topics right so on
the whole I think I think David
O'Donoghue and I like like get along and
and and share good information on this
topic but I just I think it's been
interesting like because he's curated a
lot of great art so people should go
check that out and kind of think think
of what it means to have good curation
but also think of the weaknesses we all
have in the contradictions and in
different topics and different types of
content and and what information we keep
alive and perpetuate when we're trying
to curate because I see people curating
lots of different political views which
of course I find hostile to to to
progressive movements and and to kind of
better sense making in politics
so and I guess I guess to some extent
people can give David feedback on the
art and then it becomes a kind of
collective process too because I think
he's gonna shoot in the dark tube it's
just it's just amazing to see the art
you know isn't it between curation and
censorship right there's potentially a
fine line there when you talk about
curation in that sense sorry can I sorry
Jubilee I know you've got something to
say well just that something popped into
my head as brent was talking as a as a
source of step towards collective
curating and I'm thinking in particular
about the game be Facebook group which
has kind of gone through a bit of a
rocky time of late you know a couple of
sort of senior people have left whatever
and yeah there seems to be anyway so I
was thinking something along the lines
of if you're gonna do collective
curation then you can't have one person
saying yeah this is this is appropriate
this is not appropriate so how about
something along the lines of there was
guidance from the moderators that said
something like posts that you think are
unhelpful or whatever ignore them right
don't chat just ignore them and posts
that you think are interesting and worth
developing make an effort to engage with
them in order to upregulate and what if
you've got guidance from the moderators
along along those lines to actually use
the Facebook algorithm to so try as its
you know to shine a light on the stuff
that's good and ignore the stuff that's
bad and that's no one person's decision
to decide what's good and bad
that's the group's decision to decide
what's good and bad that's that's how
does that sound I think that would be
very helpful
because of the algorithm the issue is
how do you even get that into people's
minds because how do you curate that
things to the group right if an
understanding of that of that policy was
an entry thing to the group you know
rather than you must do this you must do
this you must do this but read this
document and that short document and
that's one of the things that's in there
that I mean I'm not saying it's
foolproof I'm not saying it's perfect
but I'm saying it's maybe a first step
is what I'm saying it's you know the the
inter part that I found interesting
about that Eric was
you know the the urge to argue with and
try and change people's minds and and
the impulse that that that that comes
from I don't I don't tend to get into
that too much everyone smiles somebody
will say something that'll that'll hit a
nerve and you know having having a way
to having a way collectively to work
through that you know like not
collectively but a way to help people
work through okay I have this thing
that's coming up when I read this post
and I really want to you know and the
urge can be almost overwhelming to
respond to it and do you kick someone
out because they respond or yeah like
how do you deal with with that aspect
just as a suggestion if there's if
there's something in a post that you
think this should be down regulated so I
don't want to respond to it because that
will up regulate it right you could
write your own post about wide hat posts
triggered you yes you're not putting it
in that post you start your own one have
have any of you guys spent much time on
reddit I was just gonna say a reddit
actually because yeah you were thinking
a lot in the same lines because you can
upload and download stuff so it has a
kind of self-regulate in effect for
eight the stuff that gets a lot of is
there things that get a ton of down
votes no right because if they're
downloaded you don't see them and then
on which groups you're in cuz like my
husband goes into certain political
groups and they're you know if somebody
posts certain ideas those automatically
just get down voted and my husband
automatically down votes cats just
there's there's pro groups for certain
things and cotton groups for those same
topics right and they and they each have
their want moderators too so it's both
Democratic but also a bit a curate
and and shaped mm-hmm interests you know
I I mean I like that as a the issue is
just people knowing that because I know
I know that and I still manage to like
90% of the time I don't feed the trolls
I don't click on the click bait I don't
but then I'm like yeah I didn't want to
read that oh I didn't want to I want to
comment without reading that like I Kara
you just posted right on my page I
posted the thing about about Trump doing
something with the rivers and you were
like actually that's from two years ago
it's like yeah I totally admit I didn't
know 'we have time to research all this
stuff I just know if it's Trump
it's like yep you can tell me he
legalized you know like the killing of
kittens gonna be like yep that sounds
about right
and it's it's but like owning that piece
also that like we don't actually have
the time or the sovereign need to be
able to do all of the sense-making and
so we need to be able to curate a way to
do that without relying everyone goes
and I mean I know for me I am very
rigorous when it comes to sharing
missing people reports anytime there's a
kid that's unlike always look are they
still missing is this a proper report
and then I will share it or I will
comment on it like this kids found this
kid is because it's just like we share
it because it triggers our heartstrings
and at the same time that could be the
exact opposite of what is needed it's
like all the anyway um we have our part
that we do look into further and then
other things like if if it had been
Obama said that I might have looked into
it further right and been like wait did
he actually do that well with Trump I'm
like of course he did it could have been
a Tuesday it could have been lost
Tuesday I don't remember it from two
years ago so it's it's having yeah I'd
rather I'm going on attention thought
that was an interesting thing Jubilee
it's like there are certain things like
I have like one of the things that I
have a certain there's a couple of them
that that will bother me and cause me to
to say cause me to stop and comment and
some of those are things like lots of
comparisons of the United States to
Scandinavian countries those bug the
hell out of me
because if you look at the populate I
mean the cup the population size of all
of the Scandinavian countries together
is twenty-seven million versus America's
three hundred and twenty seven million
but to take those and compare try and
compare them just seems like
preposterous to me and and so I will
comment but there's also one of like
there's this particular meme that goes
around about people being absolutely
horrified about Social Security being
called an entitlement and like I am
somebody whose literal about words and
entitled that was what it was originally
called when it was originally really
when it was originally created when
Social Security and Medicare were
originally created because you because
if you qualified you were entitled to
the funds but everybody takes it and
here's the word entitlement and they
think that it's like that
you know oh it's something that I'm not
owed and like so it's so interesting
that the things that we like will go
into in-depth research about those are
two things that I just have this like
Bugaboo about but like anytime somebody
posts them I like feel almost compelled
to go there I can make your comments to
me is something like it's not
necessarily this job like the collective
curation yet it is like you think about
curating the museum and what we were
saying about like then it is a
collection and it's really just a
database but in a museum in a physical
space this fossil has to be somewhere so
is it based on the time period is it
based on the geography is it based on
that like what is it actually based on
whereas online on the internet we
actually can have this same thing
categorized as many different things and
if you don't like it you categorize it
as something different that we need a
new way to curate current events a way
to curate it so it's like what is
happening how do we know it's happening
why is it happening and like all of
those things get met mangled up and like
the media's the one reports on it then
we have the conversation and then they
just need clickbait titles it's like no
I want to know what's actually happening
like the thing with Trump I want the
whole timeline of everything he's said
from the environment pro and con right
not said sorry actually be cleared into
being and like to be able to curate that
is more of the
a app right it's actually putting the
information in but someone has to put
the information in and we have to have
the conversation about what gets what
gets in and what doesn't get in and I
mean I think everything but it needs to
be the UM word like boundary for is this
real or not right is it if it's for
science is an impure food journal if
it's for in events was it validated by
multiple cameras at the same time all
with the same GPS coordinates or
something that is a higher level and
then be able to understand why did this
happen and we can have more nuanced
conversations but like what happens how
do we know what happens and curating
that kind of thing well I and I think
actually that's like a perfect example
of the of the collective curation of if
somebody posts something that is you
know like we weather weather Snopes is
reliable or not or politifact you know
each one of those it's like hey I have
this counterpoint you know I have this
other piece of information that said
that goes into more detail about this
particular you know here's this here's
this explanation of why this thing is
the way it is not to not to say that
you're wrong but here's some more
information and so how we like and and
who do we you know who do we trust our
sense making to you know bringing that
in because I mean I think curation is
just an aspect of sense making like it's
and and who do I trust in my son's
making can I just say like like one one
of I think the strengths of Game me is
its initial kind of curation because
like if you can find the links and
whatnot you know you can trace back to
like a game be wiki and and posts with
like book lists and stuff so there's
quite a lot there it's been kind of pre
curated and I think that's its strengths
I think a lot it can be has a lot of
flaws and and some of that has to do
with curation and some of it has to do
kind of protocols in the way people talk
to each other which is good on one hand
right it's it's supposed to generate
sort of progress and solve issues but I
think it's also curated some brat some
bad practices in but I also wanted to
say like with with meta modernism I put
together a big spreadsheet with as many
sources I could find right and it's not
it's not a pure example of curation
because I don't have it that tagged it's
just a list if I had more time and and
and nobody else has done this either
like it was a lot of work to get it to
that point and and my incentive was to
kind of serve people's research
interests right so if you need to do
research then there is something already
sort of curated there and that's how I
think it should be done but but it's
kind of an unfinished project for me
right because I haven't I haven't tagged
at everything and so if I was to curate
it more I would go through it more in
depth and tag and you know put put meta
tags and stuff and and help people
navigate that information but it's it's
a work in progress still I know that we
don't have a ton of time left but I
realized I wanted to ask the question
what what does this group cliff see as
the difference between curation and
sense and and sense making I think to me
the searchers came up was that curation
is like the collection and organization
of the information that is still not
black and white but is much more black
and white than this sense making which
is what do I make sense of that
information or how do we collectively
make sense of it so be like pool of data
we need to agree what kind of goes in
there to a certain degree what makes
something valid and not where is my
sense making you don't actually have to
agree with even though it absolutely
affects you right what I choose to put
in my body what I choose to do in the
world is going to affect you in at the
same time unless you can change that
pool of data that I've based it on since
makings mine and the curations more
collective
mmm-hmm funny has become apparent to me
that we all of us I think that certainly
me versus the rest of you although I
think Kira and I are fairly closely in
line have very different flavors if you
like for the word curation and so Brent
it seems has a sort of largely
utilitarian kind of understanding of it
right that it's about selection and
putting in an organized fashion right it
centers around that kind of thing you
know what is appropriate and how best to
how best to organize it whereas for me
it's more about you know tending your
garden would be a form of curation that
kind of thing you know it's it's more
about maintenance and care there's love
involved in curation this kind of that
for me anyway I mean I'm just saying
this is what I bring to it I'm not
saying this is your formal definition of
the word right and so to answer your
question here what's the in-between
curation and sense making for me
curation would be kind of but it's not
as linear as this kind of what happens
after sense making and decision making
have been done the thing that has come
out of that process now needs to be
tended and looked after but also
questioned and examined ready for the
next round of sense making a decision
making right it's part of a cycle so
curation is it is part of a cycle so it
comes both before and after since making
if you like as it's part of a cycle yeah
the word that the reason I asked that
question is the thing that kept coming
to mind is the concept of outsourcing
sense making and you know in in some
cases there's too much information and
so we choose to outsource certain
aspects of our sense making to someone
else to someone else's curated narrative
of reality I think that that would be a
way I yeah appreciate that you guys
answering that case and print did you
have an aunt did you have an answer
I would just add like it makes me think
of the intellectual darkweb again to go
to go back to that kind of canard
because that was a lot of curation of
like under certain topics or memes like
free speech right like rationality like
these were the positive normative kind
of guidelines of that curation right and
that's why like I mentioned big thing at
the beginning and big think used to be a
platform that that really admired like
you know have all these public
intellectuals and big ideas but as I
matured as an independent thinker myself
I started to see big thinkers just to
kind of diluted corporate kind of
platform like like um you know and you
could see other mainstream media like
NBC kind of piggyback piggybacking the
theme and it was it was just kind of you
know do it doing a disservice to the
critical edge of of Reason which is
ultimately why we all do this but but
just to go back to your point about us
deferring sense-making to other groups
because of complexity like the
intellectual dark web is a kind of good
and bad example of this because it had
all of these ostensibly like credential
public intellectuals you know rate
ranging I like to bring in the more
innocuous ones like Steven Pinker right
like Steven Pinker is very friendly very
popular but ultimately the take away of
his message is like everything's fine
and you know the capitalism is fine
everything's fine everybody chill out
and so they decide yeah I like him as an
example though because it's it's it's
it's a you get vilified if you critique
people like him right and it just
becomes very divisive because he you
know you look at him and you look at
Jonathan hi and they're like I'm a
friendly person why would anybody
dislike me you know and it's
there's just a dark side to the curation
of this whole a kind of zeitgeist of
reason and and of and again it's what's
left out right all that like not only is
social justice left out but their whole
kind of MO is to critique social justice
is to critique post-modernism and and
not engage with those people right so
it's it's a great example of curation
gone wrong I think in a sense because
the if they've tried to just package all
the best parts of the Enlightenment
project and then completely left out
everything else let's say Merrick pops
back on others just internet but we're
just gonna wrap up because we're at the
one hour mark Kira do you have any final
one this might actually tie in to kind
of a future sub subject
brenton what you were talking about of
the kind of the dark side of you know
bringing in a shadow and how that
collective shadow and how that plays out
in curation that just be an interesting
acid how shadow plays out in curation
but in other aspects of the emergence of
game B I think that would be an
interesting thing to talk about and that
seems like a sort of part of this topic
especially when they talk about shadow -
if the group we're talking about is
curating some of this kind of shadow
talk and and like partly self criticism
and partly projecting onto others I
think it's a good meta question of that
of that curation Eric do you have any
final thoughts I were just wrapping it
up I'm you were echoing slimy to do oh
yeah no I couldn't I lost you for a
couple of minutes there my internet
connection by now I lost secret company
so I didn't hear anything anyone else
said no I don't have anything new to say
no not that I think of thank you
all right it's a goodbye to YouTube and
we'll see you next week